Last weak i put up this video about solling the game word oll,
or lest trying to solfe it,
using information tho,
and i wanted to ata quick,
a what you becallus and adendom,
a confessiono basically,
id just one explaine a place where by made a istake.
E turned out, there was iing slate bug in the coat that i was running two recreate wortl
in then bron al of the outer thems tissovit and test their performance,
and is one of those bugs that effects every small prersentade of cases,
so hey was easy to miss,
and it has only very slight effect that for the most part dosn early matter basically it
had to do with how you assin a color to a guess that has multan differet letters in it.
Reseptleith you guess speed and the truancser is abide,
how should you color those two ease from the gues,
will a wa that it works with the wortl conventions is that the first ea would be colored
yellow, and the second one would be colored gray.
You mi think of that first one is matching up with something from the true answer,
and the greenness as telling you,
there is no second e,
by contrast, if the answer was something liked inrace,
both of those ease would be coloer gillow,
helling you that there is a first e in indifferent location,
and there s a second e,
also in a different location,
the morely if one of the ease hits and its green,
then that second one would be gray in the case were the true answer has no second nen,
but it would be yellow in the case where there is a second e,
and it s jist in a diffeet mocation one stoicshwoard,
somewore along the way i axtently introduced behavior that differs from these convention
slightly. Nhonesly, it was really dumb,
bey sicly at some point in the middle of the project,
i ont an two speed up some of the computations,
and a strang a little trick for how computed the value for this pattering between any
given pair of words,
and you noi disdintreally think it through,
and it introduce the slight change.
The aronic part is it in the end,
the actual way to make things fastist is to precebute all those patterns d so tit
everything is dist a look up,
and so it wouldn t matter how long a takes to do each one,
especially a fe rating hard toread buggy coad to make it happen.
En are you live an elarn.
Mi hars how this effects,
the actual video, in very little of substance realy changes,
of course the mai lessons about what is information what is entripe all that s das the
same, every now ind them if hem showing on screen some distribution associated with ta
given word, that distribution might actually be a little bet off because some of the
buckets assucied woith batharious patterns should include either more or fewer,
true answers, even then it as a grealy come upcus as veryrare that i would be showing a
word that had munbl letters that also hit this edge case,
by orne of the very futhings of substance that does change,
and that arguably does manner a fair bit was the final conclision around how if we want
to find the optimal possible score for the wordl answerliss,
what open and guessed to such an olger the muse in the video,
i said the best performance that i confined came from opening with the word crane,
which was trew only in the sinte that the outer thems were playing a very slightly
different game. After fixing it,
and we running at all,
there is a different answer for what thef the aredically optimal first guess is for this
particular lift, an look,
i know tit you know that the point of te video is not to find some technically optimal
answer to some random on lane game.
The point of the video is deshamelessly hop on the bandwagon of an internet trind
tosneaek attack people with an information thery lesson.
A at a good, i stand by that pert,
but i nowhow the ininat works,
and for lot a people to one mayne take away was what is the best opener for the gave
wordl, and i get it,
i walked into that cas the puttit in that them now,
but presondly you can forgive me if i want ad a little correction here,
and a more meaning for reason to circle back to all this ecurally,
i that i never belly packed about what went i into that final analysis,
tan its intresting as a sublesson in it own right sopniths worth dowing here.
No if you'll recall most of our time last video was spent on the challenge of trying to
rate an olger them to solv wordol,
thit did not use the official list of all possible answers,
an i taste that feels a bit like overfitting to attest set,
and with morefine is building something bet s rasiliant.
This is why we went through the whole process of looking at relative word frequencies in
the english language to come up at some notion of how likely each on willict be toul be
included as a final anser.
However, bor what were doing here,
where weld dutrying to find an absolute best performance period,
i am inquorperating that official list and jus shame wasle overfitting to the test tat,
which is to say, we know with certainty whether a word as included or not,
and we can assigne a uniform probability to each one.
If you remember, the firt step ind all ofthis was to sai for a particular open and guess,
ay bo something like my old favourte cran,
po lingkly is it that you would see each of the possible patterns,
and in this context where we are shamelessly overfitting to the wordl answer list,
all that involvse is counting how many of the possible answers,
give euth one of these pats,
and then of course most of our time was peent on this canefany looking formula to
quantify the ament of information that you had get from this guess.
The basically involvse going through ech tont of those buckets and saying how much
information would you gain.
Tit has this log expression that is af fanciful way of saying how many times whould you
cut your space of possibilities in half if you observe to given pattern.
We take a waited average of all of those,
and it gives this amesure of how much we expects tolern from this first gess,
in a moment will go deeper than this,
but if he simply search through all thirteen thousand different words thay you could
start with, and you asked which one has the highest expected information,
etturnes out, the best possible answer is sore,
which does t really look like a real word,
but i guessot an obsolete term for a baby hack,
the top sifteen openers by this metric,
apendto look like tis,
but these are not necessarily,
the best open ind guesses,
because their only looking one step in with tha heristic of expected information,
the try to estimate what the two score will be,
but there s few enough patterns,
that we can do an exast of search two steps in,
resemble letsar you opened with sore,
and the pattern he happened a sea was temos likely one all grays then he can run
identical an lysis from that quint,
for a given proposed second guess,
something like kity,
what s the distribution across all patterns in that restricted case where were restricted
only to the words that would produce all grays for sore,
and then we measure the flatness of that distribution musing this te expected information
formila, and we do that for all thirteen thousand possible words that we could use as a
second guess, douing this we can find the opotible second guess in that scenario,
and the amount of information we ware expected to get from it,
and if wee washerancs and repeat and do this for all of the different possible pattens
that you might see, we get a full map of all the best possible second guesses together
with thexpected information of each e arn from there if you take a waited average of all
thee seconstep values weaded according to held likely you are to fall into that bucket.
They gives you a measure of how much information,
youre likely to gain from the guess sore after the second step when we use this two stepp
metric as our new means of ranking.
The list gets jacon up abit,
sor is no longer first place it fals back to fourteenth,
e instead what rises to the top is slanagain,
does t feel very real i am it looked like yit his at,
british carm for a speed.
Tit s used for cutting tush,
at, but as i can see it is of really tight race among all of hese top contenders sburt
who gains the most information after those toekh steps,
and even still these ar not necessarily the best open and guesses,
because information is just the heristic it s not telling as the actual score if you
actually play the game.
What i did as i ran the sibulation of playing all two thousand te underd fifteen possible
wortl games with all possible answers on the top two hundred fifty from this list,
then by doing this seeing how they actually perform,
the one that ins up very margnaltly with the best possible score,
on that to be sale, which is lit s e sale an alternate spelling for salla,
which is a lats maeval helmets.
As, if that feels little to to fakh for yout,
which it does for me,
wiut be happy to know that trace and creat div almost andintical performance,
each of them has the benefit of obviously being orea word,
so there is one day when you get it right on the first guess sance both our actual wordl
answers. This move from sorting bist on the best two step intrepeas to sworting bist on
thelowest avearad score,
also sheexep the list but not nearly as much,
for exemple, sale was previously third place before a bubles to the top,
and creat and trace were both forth and fifth.
If your curious, you can t get slightly better performance from here by doing a little
brote forcing. This arynice block tous by joneth and olson if you curious about this,
where he also that s you explore what the opotimale following guesses are fer a few of
distorting word based on these optomol elgar thems stepping back from all this,
though andtold by some people that at clot ruins the game to over aniline it like this
and try to find an optimal ok an a guess.
Not feels canna dirty if you huse that open ing guess after learning it,
and if yeel inefficient if you don t,
b the thing is, i don t actually think this is the best opener forar human playing the
game, foon thing, you would bee to know what the optimal second guess is fre eacht one of
the pardons that you see,
a more importantly all of this isi t a setting where we are absuredly overfit to the
official wirl answerless,
the moment it sayd the ne ork tines choeses to change what that list is under the hood,
all of this would go out the window,
beway that we humans play the game.
Is just very different from what any of these ouger hand sirdoing.
We don t have the worthlest memorized were not doing exast of searches,
we have ientuithion from things like what are the vocals and how wher they placed.
I would actually be most happy if those af you watching this midio,
pumply forgot what happens to be the technically best opening guess,
and instead came out remembering things like how do you quant to fy information ore the
fact that you should look out for when a greedy outwe them,
fal short of the glibly best performance that you a get from a eper search,
to my tast at least the joy of writing outwer thems to try to ple games,
acuias very little bearing on how i like to play those games as a human,
the point of riting ougerthams fr al this is not to effect the way that we played the
game, and still dus to fundwart gam.
It s te hone in our muscles for writing out wer thems an more meeting ful context
telswerer a ad d a, e hd a oo o i a olo lan iaa lin o loalololmloelon.