Lu moe the phrase exponential groath is familiar to most people,
and yet human intuition has a hard time really recondizing what it mean,
sometimes we can anchor on assequence a small seming numbers and then become surprised
ben suddenly those number s looked big,
even if, the overall trend follows and exponential perfectly consistend mit.
This rechere is the daterfor the recorded cases oof covid nineteen,
aca a the coron ofvirous,
lelishe at the time that im writing this never one to wast an opportunity for a
matlesson, i thet this might be good time for all of us to go back to the basix on whan
exponential groth really is where it comes trom what id implies,
and lay be most pressingly how to know when it s coming to an end,
exponential growth means that as you go from one day to the next in evals multiplying by
some constant in aurdata,
the number of tases in each day tense to be a multble of about one point on five to one
ting two five of the number of cleaves the previous day,
navirices are a tex pook example of this candor groth,
because what causes new cases are the existent cases,
so if the number of cases on a given day is an,
and we say that each individual witthevirous is exposed to onaverage e people on a given
day, and each one of those exposures had the probability conn of decoming a new infection
than the number of new cases on a given day is etimes pe times an,
and the factoid, and itself is a factor in its own change is what really makes things go
fast, because if an gets big.
A means the rec of growth itself is getting big.
One we to think about this is that as you add the new cases to get the next day s count.
You can fact er out the en,
soits just the same is multiplying by some constant that s bigger than one.
This is sometimes easier to see if we put the wy exiss of egrafh on a ligwithmixcale,
which means that each step of a fix distance,
corsponstim bultepplying by a certain factor.
Mis case each step is another power of ten on the scale,
exponential growth should look like a straight line,
looking at ardata, it seems like it took twenty days to go from one hundred to one
thousand and thirteen days to go from that to ten thasand,
and if you do a thimble linnior regression to find the best fit line.
You coul look at the slope of that line to draw a conclusion like we cintimble teply by
ten every sixteen days on aperage,
this regression also that this belittle more quantitative about exactly how close the
expinetial fit really is,
and to use the technicl s statistical jargon here.
Answers that it s really freekinclips,
but i can be heart tod gi just exactly whath that means if true when you see one country
witsay six thousand cases,
and another with sixty.
It easy to think but the second as doing a hundredtimes better and hence fine,
but if your actually an asiuation were numbers multiply by ten every sixteen days,
another way to view the same fact is that the second country is about a month behind the
ferst. A disis, of course,
rather worrying if you dryw out the vine.
I m recording this on march six,
and if the presentran continues,
it would mean hiding million cases in thirty days,
hitding ten billin in forty seven days,
a hundred million ind sixty four days,
and one lilian in eighty one days.
Met was to say, though you can t us driw out a line like this frever,
the clearly has to starts slowing down at semppy,
but the crucial question is win,
is it liked the sirs outbreak of two thousin two,
which kept out around eigh thousand cases or the spanish lee of nignteen eighteen,
which ultimately infected about twenty seven persent of the world s population ingeneral
with no context just drawing a line throu your data is not a great way to make
predictions, but remember,
there s an actual beason to expect an exponential here.
If the number of new cases each day is proportional to the number of existing cases.
It necessarily means each day umol replied by some constant,
some boving forward de days is the same as miltiploiingt by that constant te times,
the only way that stops as it either the number en,
or pe gos down. It s inevitable that this will eventually happen,
even in the most perfectly pernicious model for ofvirous,
which would be where every day,
each person with the infection is exposed to a rand om subset of the world population.
At some point most of the people theyre exposed to would aready be sick,
and so they could t become your casets in our ecuasion that would mean that the
probability of an exposure becoming a new infection would have to include some kine
effector to account for the probability that some one your exposed two is already
infected for a random shuffling midte likeness,
that could mean including factor like one miness,
the proportion of people in the world who were already infected,
including that factor in inselving for how and grows.
You get whats known in the business as a logistic curve,
which is dessentually indistinguishable from an exponential at the beteening,
but ultimately at levels out once your approaching the total population sas,
which is what you would expect,
true expinentials dessentilly never existend the rea world,
every one of them is belyed the start of a legistin curv of this point rig care were that
logistic goes from crivving upward to insted curving downward is known as the inflection
point there the number of new cases each day,
represented by the slope of this curve,
stopps increasing, and instead tays roughly constant before starts decreason,
so one number, the people often follow with epademix is the groth factor,
which is difined as thracia between the number of new cases one day,
and the number of new cases the previous day,
so just to beclear if you were looking at all of the totals from one day to the next then
tracking te changes between those totals,
the grothfactor is a racial between two successive changes.
While youre on the exponential part,
this factor stays consistently above one.
Whereis a soon as your grothfactor look claser to one.
It s assign that you ve hit the inflection.
This can mike for another counter into it af fact while following the dava,
think abut what it would feel like for the number of new cases one day to be about ficten
percent more than the number of new cases the previous day,
and contrast that with what it would feo like for to be about the same,
just looking at the totals,
they resulted. They don t weally feel that different,
but if the grotfactor is one,
thet couol mean year the inflection point of aligistic,
which would mean the totl number of cases is gin a max out atd about two times wherever
you are now, but a grothfactor bigger than one settled that might seem means ere on the
exponential part, which could impli there are orders of magnitude of growth still waiting
a head of you. Nou whileit s true that in the worst tasituation the saturation poaint is
around the total population.
It s of course not at all true that people with te virous are rendon wah cheffled around
the worlds population likeness,
people are cluster to in local communities.
However, if you ren simulations fere this numen of little bid of travel between plusters
likeness. The growth is actually not that much different what you went up with is a kind
of fractal pattern were communities themselves sfunks and like individuals,
each one has some exposiour to others with some probability at spreading the infection,
said the same underlying and expenintu inducing the laws apply or moonelmormoor ol
fortunately, saturating the whole population is not the only thing they can cause the two
factors we care about to go down.
The mantal exposure can also go down when people stoppdgathering in travelling,
an the infectionary can go down when people just wash their handsmore.
The other thing that counterantuative about expinentiral broth,
thi time in a more optimistic sens is just houe sincitive it is to this constant,
for exemple, if it s fifteen percent like it is as ammrecorting this,
and were at twenty one thousand cases now that would mean tat sixty one days from now,
you had over a hundred milliam by if through a bit less exposure and infection that re
drops down to five per cent.
It do nit ean the projection also dropps down by factor of three,
tet equally dropps down to around four hundred thousand,
so of people ar sufficiently worried than there s awatless to wory about,
but if no one is worried that s when you should woring e aole ano a one a.