The magini happen across a short mulyscript that describes a seme between a person,
and their a i assistant,
thescriptd has what the person asks the a eye,
but the aeyes respons has been tourn off.
Suppose you also have this powerful magical machine the cantake any text and provide a
sensible prediction of what word comes next.
They could then an finished dhescript by feeding ind what you have to the machine,
seeing what it would predict to start the aeyes answer,
and then repeating this over and over with a growing script,
completing the dialog.
When you an errant with a chat but,
this is exactly whats happening,
a large language model is a sophisticated mathmadical function that predicts what word
comes next for any piece of tex,
instead of predicting one word with certainty,
though what it does is assign a probability to all possible next words to build a chat
but what you do is lay outsome tex that describes an interaction between a user and a
hypothetical a e assistant.
You at on whatever the user tapesin as the first part of that ineraction,
and then you have the model repeatedly prodict the next word tat such a hyhpathetical
aasisten would say in response,
and that s what s presented to the user.
In doing this the outquictins to look a what more natural if you allow at ti slect less
likely words along the way at random,
so with this meansas even though the movel itself is deterministic,
ta given permptd, tipically gives a different answer each time it s run,
modtels learn how to make these predictions by processing an enormous amount of text,
tipically pulled from the internate for ats anderd human to red the imount of text it was
used to train a ce pe te three firds emple,
if they read non stopp twenty for seven.
E would take over twenty six hundred years,
larger model since then train onmuch much more.
Te can think a training a little bit like tuning the dials on a big machine,
the way that a language model behaves is entirely determined by these many different
continuous values, usually called perametors or weats,
changing those perametors or change the probabilities that the modtlgins for the next
word on a given implit,
what puts the large in large language model is how they can have hundreds of bilians of
these perametors. No human ever deliberately sets those parameters instead,
they begin it random,
eining the model just output s gibberish,
but there repeatedly refined bases on many example pieces of text.
One of the straining examples could be just a handfull of words,
where i could be thousins,
but in either taste,
the way this works is to pass in all but the last word from that example into the model
and compared the prodiction that it makes with the true last word from the example,
and ouder them called back propagation is used to tweek all of the pramaters in such away
that it makes the model olit te more likely to choose the true last word,
an a little less likely to choose all the others.
When you do this for many mani trilians of examples,
not only does the modelstar to give more accurat predictions on the treaning data,
but it alsospets to make more reasonable predictions urtext that it s never seen before,
given the huge number of paramitors and the enormous amount of training data,
the scale of computation involved intraining a larchelanguich movel is mind buggling,
talustrate imagine that you could perform one lilian additions and multiplications every
single second. How on do you think that it would take for you to do all of the operations
involved intraining the largest language models.
Do you think you an take,
a year may be something like ten thousand years.
Tha nswer is actually much more than that it s well over one hundred melian years.
This is only part of the story,
though this while process is called retraining,
the gol of oto completing a random passage of tex from the internante was very different
from the gol of being a good a i assistant to address this,
chat bots undergo another type of training,
just as important, called reinforcement learning with human feet back,
workers flag unhelpfull their problematic predictions,
and their corrections further change the model s perimeters,
making them more likely to give predictions that users prefer,
looking backet the pretraning though this staggering amount of computation is only made
possible by using special competer chips that are optimized for running many many
operations in perale,
known as copy yous, however,
not all linguine models can be easily perilalized,
pryer to twenty seventeen,
most linguigh models would process text one were ta atine,
but then a tem of te serchters at gogol,
introduced a new model known as the transformer,
transformers don t read text from the start to the finish,
the so culd all in at once in parallo,
the very first step inside a transformer len most other language models for that matter
is to associate each word with a long wist of numbers,
the reason for this is that thetraining process only works with continuous values,
soou have to somehow incode language using numbers,
an each oe these lest of numbers may somehow incod the meaning of the corresponding word,
bhut maks transformers unique is there reliance ona special operation known as attention.
This operation gives all of these lists of numbers,
a chance to talk to one another,
and refined the meanings that they incode,
basted on the context around all thene in perallo,
for exemple the numbers incoting the word,
bank might be changed bast on the context surrounding it to somehow into the mor pacific
notion of a river bank,
genc formers tipically also include a second take of operationknown,
is e feed forward narrow that work,
and this gives the moval extricapacity to store more patterns about language learned
during training, all of thi stata repeatedly flows through many different iarations of
these two fundamental operations,
and as a desse, the hope is that each list of numbers is inwiched to encode whatever
information might be needed to make an accurate prediction of what word follows in the
passage at the end, one final function is performed on the last vector in this sequence,
which now has had a chance to be influictd by all the other context from the inpottext,
as while as everything the molter learnd during training to produce a prodiction of the
next word again, the model s prediction it looks like a probability for every possible
next word, although researcher s design the frame work for how each of the step s work,
it s important understand that thispacific behagor is an emergent phenomenon,
based unhow those hundreds of billions of perametors are tuned,
during training. This mensip incredibly challenging to determine why the model maks the
exact predictions that it does what you can t see is that when you use large language
model predictions to oto complete apprompt,
the words, the degenerates aret uncanaly fluent faccinating,
and peven useful if your a newvewre and your curious about more details anyhow
transformers and attention work by do i have so material for you,
wonuction is too jump in to a series i made about deplearning where we fisur wilize and
noti ate, the details of attention,
and all the other steps in a transformer,
but also im my sa ontinal,
i just posted to talk tat i cave a cuplements ago about thi totic for the company tea in
ge in unin omtems i aclleve trefer the content that i make as the casual tack rather tan
a pretties tidio bet i leaved up to you which on a these hails like the better follow on
a mola momer an i moeamomore moreo alaa oa a ao.